P.O. Box 1630, Eldoret 30100, Kenya

Mobile: +254 721 969 956 E-mail: linus@linuschirchir.com Website: www.linuschirchir.com

## Linus K. Chirchir

# **Profile**



Accomplished Healthcare Information Technology Professional with over II years' experience managing server infrastructures and data-centre operations across multiple platforms (Windows, Unix and Linux). Effectively plan, install, configure and optimize the ICT infrastructure to consistently achieve high availability and performance. Proven ability to create and deliver solutions tied to organizational growth, development and systems/network optimization. Skilled problem identifier and troubleshooter comfortable managing systems, projects and teams in a range of ICT environments.



Microsoft

CERTIFIED

Solutions Expert Server Infrastructure

Certifications CCNP: Cisco Certified Network Professional: Routing and Switching, Starting October, 2015.

> CCNA: Cisco Certified Network Associate: Routing and Switching, Starting September, 2015.

> MCSE: Microsoft Certified Solutions Expert: Server Infrastructure, Starting May, 2015.

**MCP:** Microsoft Certified Professional, Starting April, 2015.

MCSA: Microsoft Certified Solutions Associate: Windows Server 2012, Starting April, 2015.

# **Training**

ISO/IEC 27001:2013 Information Security Management Systems Internal Auditor Course, 20th - 22nd June 2018 at Cicada Hotel, Eldoret.

ISO/IEC 27001:2013 Information Security Management Systems **Lead Implementer Course**, 13<sup>th</sup> – 14<sup>th</sup> and 16<sup>th</sup> June 2018 at Cicada Hotel, Eldoret.

Grant Writing and Project Management, 14th November 2017 – 15th November 2017 at the Noble Hotel, Eldoret.

Senior Management Course, 29th August 2016 - 23rd September 2016 at Kenya School of Government, Lower Kabete, Nairobi.

Project Management Professional Training, 1st February 2016 - 12th February 2016 at Harmony Solutions Limited, Nairobi.

Red Hat Linux 7 Administration I and II Training, 21st September 2015 - 2<sup>nd</sup> October 2015 at the Institute of Software Technologies, Nairobi.





September 2018 - August 2019, Chandaria School of Business, United States International University - Africa. | Nairobi, Kenya: Master of Business Administration. **Project:** Factors Influencing Electronic Health Records Adoption by Nurses at Moi Teaching and Referral Hospital, Eldoret, Kenya.









January 2014 - December 2015, Kisii University | Kisii, Kenya: Master of Information Systems. Thesis: Effects of Health Information Systems on user Performance: A Survey of Health Organizations in Uasin Gishu County, Kenya.

**September 2008 - December 2012, Moi University | Eldoret, Kenya:** Bachelor of Business Management (Business Information Systems Management).

**January 2001 - November 2003, Eldoret Polytechnic | Eldoret, Kenya:** Kenya National Examinations Council Technical Education Programme Diploma in Computer Studies.

January 1995 - November 1998, Nyansiongo High School | Nyansiongo, Kenya: Kenya Certificate of Secondary Education.

January 1987 - November 1994, St. Andrews Kaggwa Boys Boarding Primary | Nyansiongo, Kenya: Kenya Certificate Primary Education.

# **Experience**

# **Professional Experience**

November 2019 - Present, Moi Teaching and Referral Hospital | Eldoret, Kenya: Deputy Manager, ICT. Duties and Responsibilities at this level entails designing, implementing and maintaining the Hospital's ICT infrastructure; designing and implementing capabilities to ensure information system security; developing, implementing and managing computerized information systems; formulating and implementing ICT policies, procedures and plans; managing third party service providers of ICT services to ensure that the Hospital gets value for money; managing ICT related projects through the complete project lifecycle from project initiation to project closure, including project review, undertaking proactive monitoring of costs, timescales and resources throughout; identifying ICT needs of the Hospital staff and clients; providing ICT services to transform the Hospital into an automated work environment that supports efficient and effective service delivery; providing appropriate information and guidance on emerging trends and best practices in ICT to enable Hospital optimize usage of technology; providing support for users of Hospital's ICT services; conducting and coordinating user training on various systems e.g. HMIS, ERP etc.; ensuring the ICT strategies, procedures and plans are complete, current and accurate; organizing regular testing of disaster recovery plans and document outcomes; documenting and implementing appropriate processes to manage and report on all ICT infrastructure and systems changes; deputizing for the Manager, ICT.

November 2016 - October 2019, Moi Teaching and Referral Hospital | Eldoret, Kenya: Senior ICT Officer. Provide Windows/Unix/Linux administration, Integrated Healthcare Management Information Systems (I-HMIS) administration, LAN/WAN/VPN administration and intrusion detection and prevention monitoring. Also, manage FTP servers, AD/DNS and wireless access points. Design and



implement highly available and disaster recovery solutions for the employer.

### **Selected Achievements**

Initiated the acquisition and deployment of G Suite for Education solution which includes the following core services: Classroom, Mail, Calendar, Drive, Docs, Sheets, Groups, Vault, Sites, Forms, and Hangouts that saves the hospital more than 19.03 million shillings annually and consequently permanently solved the perennial interruptions of internal and external organizational communication.

November 2014 - October 2016, Moi Teaching and Referral Hospital | Eldoret, Kenya: ICT Officer II. Charged with overseeing system installations, as well as monitoring and maintaining the organization's ICT servers and evaluating new server hardware and software.

#### **Selected Achievements**

Implemented the OpenMRS EMR at Moi Teaching and Referral Hospital.

July 2008 – October 2014, Moi Teaching and Referral Hospital | Eldoret, Kenya: ICT Officer III. Maintained, installed and troubleshot computers and information systems.

#### **Selected Achievements**

Deployed the Network Computing Desktop Virtualization at Memorial Private Wing II, Moi Teaching and Referral Hospital.

**January 2004 - July 2008, Self-employed: Freelance ICT Technician.** Provided support for the deployment and maintenance of computer infrastructure and web technology and the diagnosis and resolution of technical problems.

## **Service**

#### **Professional Service**

**December 2019 - Present,** Moi Teaching and Referral Hospital | Eldoret, Kenya: Member, Quality Improvement Team.

**February 2017 - Present,** Moi Teaching and Referral Hospital | Eldoret, Kenya: Member, Hospital ICT Committee.

**February 2017 - October 2019,** Moi Teaching and Referral Hospital | Eldoret, Kenya: Chair, Hospital Disposal Committee.

### **Community Service**

**August 2015 - Present,** St. Clement Secondary School, Nyigoon | Eldoret, Kenya: Vice Chair, Board of Management.



**Member,** Healthcare Information Management Systems Society (HIMSS), Starting August, 2017.

**Member,** Project Management Institute (PMI), Starting February, 2016.

**Member,** Information Systems Audit and Control Association (ISACA), Starting May, 2015.

**Member**, Association for Information Systems (AIS), Starting October, 2013. Served on the Awards and Recognition Subcommittee of the AIS Membership Committee.



Research

**Member,** Rotary Club of Eldoret – Uasin Gishu, Starting March, 2018. Served as the Sergeant at Arms for 2018 – 2019 Rotary Year. Serving as the Director, Public Image for 2019 – 2020 Rotary Year.

#### **Publications**

Aruasa, W. K., **Chirchir, L. K.**, & Chebon, S. K. (2019). <u>Implications of Physicians and Nurses' Professional Satisfaction on Patient Care</u>. *International Journal of Public Health Science (IJPHS)*, 8 (3), 300 – 306. DOI: 10.11591/ijphs.v8i3.20238

Chebon, S. K., Aruasa, W. K., & Chirchir, L. K. (2019). Effect of Inspirational Motivation and Idealized Influence on Employee Performance at Moi Teaching and Referral Hospital, Eldoret, Kenya. International Journal of Business and Social Science, 10(7), 131 – 140. DOI:10.30845/ijbss.v10n7p14

Aruasa, W. K., **Chirchir, L. K.,** & Chebon, S. K. (2019). <u>Determinants of Physicians and Nurses' Professional Satisfaction at the Moi Teaching and Referral Hospital, Eldoret, Kenya</u>. *Journal of Health, Medicine and Nursing*, 64, 6 – 17. DOI: 10.7176/JHMN



Aruasa, W. K., **Chirchir, L. K.,** & Chebon, S. K. (2019). <u>Strategies for Improving Physicians and Nurses' Professional Satisfaction at the Moi Teaching and Referral Hospital, Eldoret, Kenya</u>. The Strategic Journal of Business & Change Management, 6 (3), 216 – 226.

Chebon, S. K., Aruasa, W. K., & Chirchir, L. K. (2019). <u>Influence of Individualized Consideration and Intellectual Stimulation on Employee Performance: Lessons from Moi Teaching and Referral Hospital, Eldoret, Kenya</u>. *IOSR Journal of Humanities and Social Science*, 24 (7), 11 – 22. DOI: 10.9790/0837-2407041122

**Chirchir, L. K.**, Aruasa, W. K., & Chebon, S. K. (2019). <u>Perceived Usefulness and Ease of Use as Mediators of the Effect of Health Information Systems on User Performance</u>. European Journal of Computer Science and Information Technology, 7 (1), 22 – 37.

Ireri, E. N., Omondi, Y. A., **Chirchir, L. K.**, & Wafula, M. K. (2015). Adoption of Enterprise Resource Planning System in Kenya: A Case Study of Kenya Ordnance Factories Corporation. International Journal of Current Research, 7 (4), 14702 – 14711.

#### Referees

**Dr. Wilson K. Aruasa, MBS,** Chief Executive Officer, Moi Teaching and Referral Hospital. P.O. Box 3 - 30100, Eldoret, Kenya. Mobile: +254 727 415 377 / +254 733 869 760 E-mail: ceo@mtrh.go.ke

**Dr. Thomas Mwogi,** Chief Information Officer, Moi Teaching and Referral Hospital. P.O. Box 3 - 30100, Eldoret, Kenya. Mobile: +254 722 256 327 E-mail: cio@mtrh.go.ke

**Prof. Jimmy K. N. Macharia,** Associate Professor of Information Systems and Technology, School of Science and Technology, United States International University - Africa. P.O. Box 14634 - 00800, Nairobi, Kenya. Mobile: +254 722 779 770 E-mail: kmacharia@usiu.ac.ke